בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is צדיק א׳, Tzaddik Alef,
ninety-one. We pick up six lines from the
bottom, five lines from the bottom. איתמר, Itmar, is that where we
left off? Anybody? I wasn't here, but that's where I stopped. Okay,
or תנו רבנן Tanu Rabanan maybe? That's right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. Six lines from the bottom, seven lines from
the bottom. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan: החוסם את הפרה והמזווג בכלאיים, Hachosem
et haparah vehamezaveg bekilayim, if somebody muzzles the cow or puts
the animals together that are not supposed to be
cross-bred or threshing together,
פטור, patur, you're exempt. But he's not breeding them, it's putting them
together on a yoke. On a yoke in order that they should
then, right, be, that's what I said, like to thresh together, to
work together, whatever. ואינו לוקה אלא דש ומנהיג בלבד. V'ein lo loke
ela dash u'manhig bilvad. So the person is not the person that
put the muzzle on, but it's
like the person that actually does the threshing with the cow, which
is interesting because it says לא תחסום שור בדישו, Lo sachsom shor
bedisho, don't muzzle it in its threshing. But the גמרא Gemara understands
that the muzzling of it, you can muzzle it and not use
it, so that's not actually the איסור. issur. The איסור issur is
at the moment of threshing, so it's only the person that does
the threshing with the ox. And similarly, it's only the person, it
says like what's the פסוק pasuk by
כלאיים, kilayim, לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו. Lo sachrosh beshor uvachamor yachdav.
Is that it?
לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו. Lo sachrosh beshor uvachamor yachdav. So it's
the act actually of the, yeah,
לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו. Lo sachrosh beshor uvachamor yachdav. So anyway,
it's actually the act of the threshing, not the act that precedes
it, not the act of yoking them together. גמרא Gemara yesterday explained
that you put the muzzle
on, yeah, the גמרא Gemara yesterday spoke about that if you muzzled
it outside, there's a question what happened if you muzzled it outside
and then you did it after, right? But this is actually the
person that puts the muzzle on is not the one who does
it.
I would have to look again at the דף daf yesterday, we're
going back a while. Anyway,
okay.
חסמה מבחוץ מהו? Chasmah babachutz mahu? הרי דש בדישו
ועליו בדישו או דילמא לא תדוש בחסימה רחמנא. Hersh bedisho v'alav bedisho
o dilma lo sadush bechasima rachmana. Right, says the גמרא Gemara no,
the גמרא's Gemara conclusion of the גמרא Gemara was that even if
you muzzled it outside, you're חייב chayav then when you actually do
the threshing. But that the question was was that but it wasn't
that you'd be חייב chayav at the moment of muzzling. The question
is if you separated the two, would you be חייב chayav at
the moment of threshing and the answer is yes. But here the
גמרא Gemara is saying that the transgression is the one who does
the threshing, not the one who did the muzzling beforehand, and the
transgression is the one who leads the ox and the donkey together,
not the one who yoked them together. Yes. Is there any discussion
about what the reasoning behind that, the ox and the donkey, or
is it just a גזירה? gezeirah? I mean, the מפרשים meforshim give
different reasons. I mean, the one that people like because it works
more with modern sensibilities is that like they go at different rates
so you're not like a צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim type
of an issue. But it seems that in general it's just the
broader תורה's Torah concern of the whole cross-breeding. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: איתמר. Itmar. All right, anyway that was the
ending up yesterday's discussion, that it's the actual act that's doing them.
איתמר. Itmar. Now was taught, now back to a different point.
חסמה בקולו והנהיגה בקולו. Chasmah bekolo vehinhigah bekolo. Let's say, now that
we've identified that it's through the act of muzzling or leading it,
let's say you accomplished this through using your voice. You yelled at
it and you had them yoked together and you yelled at them
and then they moved
forward.
Or let's say you didn't muzzle the animal and it was threshing
and you yelled at it and it stopped eating because it was
afraid of your yells. Now that's a little interesting because a minute
ago we said that actually the person who does the muzzling is
not חייב, chayav, but it's only the person who actually makes it
thresh.
But presumably that's because the muzzling took place prior to the act
of threshing. If you yell at it, so you are muzzling it
during the act of threshing, the גמרא Gemara assumes that that would
be you should be liable. But the question is is the act
of yelling itself doing an action, not to get lashes? You've transgressed,
but is it an action? Correct. So רבי יוחנן אמר חייב, Rabbi
Yochanan amar chayav, you transgressed, ריש לקיש אמר פטור, Reish Lakish amar
patur, you do not. רבי יוחנן אמר חייב, Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav,
עקימת פיו הוי מעשה. Akimat piv havei ma'aseh. Like he says why
do we necessarily distinguish like we say only an act that you
get a transgression that you get an action you get
lashes, but moving your lips is also an action. What should it
matter if it's like you moved your pinky and you flicked on
a light on Shabbos? or something like that or if you moved
your lips and you yelled? Right, it's still using a part of
your body to do something, so why is that any less of
an action? ריש לקיש אמר פטור, Reish Lakish amar patur, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says you're exempt. קלא לא הוי מעשה kala lo havei
ma'aseh because even though it was achieved through moving your lips, ultimately
what did the work was your voice, and your voice is not
your, is not the, your body. So it's not something that was
accomplished through your body, it was something that was accomplished through your
voice. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, Eitiveih Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan challenges ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. לא ישנה אדם לשלם
להמיר, Lo yishneh adam l'shalem l'hamir, it says that if you do
תמורה, tmurah, לא ימיר אותו, lo yamir oto, you try to have
an animal that's sanctified for a קרבן korban and you try to
exchange it with another animal, so the other animal also becomes קדוש.
kadosh. So the משנה Mishnah says it's not that you're allowed to
do this, אלא אם המיר מומר, ela im hemir mumar, but if
you actually did try to exchange, the second animal, it's effective, the
second animal becomes קדוש kadosh and וסופג
את הארבעים v'sofeg et ha'arbaim and you get forty lashes. So look
over there, you get lashes for just doing something with your mouth,
so you see something verbal is considered an act. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, הא מני רבי יהודה היא דאמר לאו שאין בו מעשה
לוקין עליו. Ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi d'amar lav she'ein bo ma'aseh
lokin alav.
That's only רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you get lashes for
not doing an act, even for a transgression without an act. That
doesn't prove that it counts as an act. So the גמרא Gemara
says וממאי דמוקמת לה כרבי יהודה, u'mimai d'mokmat lah k'Rabbi Yehuda, how
could you say it's רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? והקתני רישא הכל ממירין,
V'hakatani reisha hakol memirin, אחד האנשים ואחד הנשים, echad ha'anashim v'echad ha'nashim,
anybody can do an act of
תמורה, tmurah, whether a man or a woman. והוינא בה הכל לאתויי
מאי, v'havina bah hakol l'atuyei mai, what's it coming to include?
לאתויי יורש, L'atuyei yoresh, if you are an heir. If a person's
father dies and leaves him over a קרבן, korban, so only the
owner of the קרבן korban can do תמורה. tmurah. Let's say you're
not the original owner of the קרבן, korban, you only inherited it.
Would your attempt to try to exchange it for another animal, would
that be just meaningless because you're not the owner, or since you
did inherit the animal even though you weren't the one that sanctified
it, you are considered the owner and it is an act of
תמורה? tmurah? So the גמרא Gemara says the משנה Mishnah there that
says everybody can do it even includes a יורש, yoresh, somebody who
inherited it. And that's somebody who's enough the owner to do תמורה.
tmurah. ודלא כרבי יהודה, V'dla k'Rabbi Yehuda, and that goes against רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דרבי יהודה אמר יורש אינו מימיר, D'Rabbi Yehuda amar
yoresh eino memir, יורש אינו סומך. yoresh eino somech. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says an heir who inherits a קרבן korban is not the
owner of the קרבן. korban. If he does תמורה tmurah it's meaningless.
Also if he brings the קרבן, korban, let's say it's a שלמים
shlamim and not a
חטאת, chatas, so it can be brought because the, even if the
owner's dead. Nevertheless, he would not do סמיכה, smichah, he would not
put his hands on the קרבן korban because he's not the owner.
So therefore it's clearly therefore the author of our משנה Mishnah that
anybody can do תמורה, tmurah, which we interpret to mean including a
יורש, yoresh, is not רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So therefore how could
you say that the reason you get lashes is because it goes
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you get lashes without an
act? Clearly the משנה Mishnah is not רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
you removed רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's authority from the opinion that the
voice is like a body part? Right, we first have to assume
the משנה Mishnah says you get lashes, is the משנה Mishnah assuming
you need an act or not assuming you need an act? And
we first tried to say, well maybe it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who doesn't need an act. It says no, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
clearly is not the author of this משנה. Mishnah. Just to give
you a reminder, as I said, if you do this תמורה, tmurah,
the תמורה tmurah is קדוש kadosh and you get lashes? Yes, that's
what I said, correct. So the גמרא Gemara says דאי רבי יהודה,
d'ei Rabbi Yehuda, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says no, האי תנא
סבירא ליה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. Hai tana savira lei kavateih
b'chada u'palig aleih b'chada. No, it's a classic answer of the גמרא,
Gemara, that just because the author of the משנה Mishnah does not
agree with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about the idea of יורש yoresh
and thinks that a יורש yoresh is an heir and would do
תמורה, tmurah, it doesn't mean that he disagrees with רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda about the issue of lashes. And maybe the author of the
משנה Mishnah thinks you get lashes without an act. So even though
it's true that in that משנה Mishnah you get lashes for speech,
for an act of speech, for תמורה, tmurah, that doesn't necessarily mean
that that's considered an act. That might be following the position of
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Now, I do want to say something.
תוספות Tosafos has a large discussion about the גמרא Gemara seems to
be inconsistent about this question about whether speech is considered an act
and so on. And תוספות Tosafos tries to make a number of
distinctions. A major point of distinction of תוספות Tosafos is whether your
speech
leads to a real-world effect.
So for example if somebody gives testimony in court, so that's a
speech that brings about an action, that actually gets
somebody executed. And here,
I think here, hold on,
let me just take a look,
one minute.
Yeah, so that's what he says. So תוספות Tosafos says the same
thing is true over here because here too your speech leads to
an action, right? The action that your speech led to was that
it caused the cow to stop eating, right? It effectively muzzled the
cow. So if you do certain types of speech acts, a speech
which would not lead to an action is let's
say somebody he... blasphemed God, right? Or you know, like לא תקלל
חרש, lo tekallel cheresh, right? Or cursed somebody, or whatever. Like those
are types of speech acts that don't actually have any real-world effect.
Okay?
So those types of acts are acts that are speech acts without,
you know, which are more likely to be considered not an action.
And תוספות Tosafot says part of the issue here is that both
of these speech acts lead to an action. One is that it
sanctifies the animal when you do תמורה. temurah. The other animal becomes
sanctified, so speech had some real-world effect, right? And the other is
that your speech act silenced the cow. So that's one way תוספות
Tosafot says that that's maybe more of a reason that this speech
act be considered an action rather than other speech acts. I think
that there's something else going on here as well, which is the
difference between voice and speech, because, right, if we're talking about a
question of let's say, of let's say bearing testimony, or even like
blaspheming or whatever, the idea of speech in that context is a
sort of external manifestation of my thoughts, right? It's giving voice to
my thoughts. But there the fundamental meaning of that thing is the
ideas, right, that are expressed in my words. So that's really not
something that we just translate into a physical action. That's something that's
much more about, you know, my voice, my thoughts as they are
expressed. Whereas here, not in the case of תמורה, temurah, but in
the case of חסימה, chasima, it has not
there's no question of the meaning of your words. It's just your
sound, right? The very sound waves that you are creating, those loud
sound waves, startle the cow and silence it. So that is something
that is much more fully part of the physical world, right? It's
just a purely physical effect. So the same way if I hit
somebody or I turn on a light or I do something with
my body, if I move my lips and I create sound waves,
right, if I hit some if I hit like water and it
creates ripples and it goes ahead and it does something, that would
be an action. So if I move my lips and create sound
waves and it startles the cow, that's a purely physical type of
an act, right? And I think in that way this is very
different than other questions of the גמרא Gemara where speech is an
action, because there it much more has to do with the words
that I said and the meaning behind the words. So that's at
least what I think is a little bit going on here, although
it doesn't fit with the גמרא Gemara
about תמורה. temurah. Okay. ובשאמר. U've'she'amar. What? ובשאמר, U've'she'amar, spoken the world
was created. Right, exactly. The whole bar... well, that's true, no, but
part of the whole point is that even without an action God
created the world. But you know, yes, but that would be תוספות's
Tosafot example that of words that create a real-world effect. Right? But
anyway, but I guess you have all three possibilities. Right? You have
this, which is something that's not about words at all, that's just
about sound, and that's purely almost like a physical reality, and that's
I then I find רבי יוחנן's Rebbe Yochanan position very persuasive. What
do I care if I hit water and create ripples and that
does something, or if I move my lips and create sound waves
and that does something? It's all about a physical reality. Right? Then
you have speech that just exists in the world of speech and
thought, right? I say something to you, you think something, or whatever,
there's no physical effect. And then you have what תוספות Tosafot talks
about which is a speech act which creates a physical effect, like
testifying in court or, you know, doing trying to do תמורה temurah
of an animal. Okay. And if you yell at somebody... Right. The
yelling is both. It's a physical it's purely about the physical act,
not about the speech act and about the physical effect. Exactly. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. תנו רבנן החוסם
את פרתו ודש בה, Tanu Rabbanan: Hachosem et parato ve'dash bah, somebody
muzzles a cow and then threshes with it, לוקה ומשלם ארבעה קבין
לפרה וג' קבין לחמור. lokeh u'mishalem arba'ah kabbin le'parah ve'gimel kabbin le'chamor.
So not only has this person transgressed the biblical prohibition of threshing
with a muzzled ox, but the person has robbed the owner of
the ox's lunch. The ox had a right to be eating. So
you have a financial, you know, liability to the owner for that
to pay what the ox would have eaten or what the donkey
would have eaten. Okay. So you actually have גזילה gezeila against the
animal?
Well, it's against the owner of the animal.
Right. I mean, this assumes that there's another owner there. If it
was your own ox, because it's also a prohibition of muzzling your
own ox, right, you would not have to pay back your ox.
But if it's somebody else's ox, then you have two things going
on here. So the גמרא Gemara says והא אין לוקה ומת ואין
לוקה ומשלם, ve'ha ein lokeh u'mes u've'ein lokeh u'mishalem, how can you
have two things? How can you have lashes and you can't get
lashes and be put to death, and you can't get lashes and
pay somebody? So you can't have two liabilities to the owner. So
picking up on Charlie's point, תוספות Tosafot says, you know, you could
have a case where your liabilities are to different people, which is
that I basically what would it be?
תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question, hold on.
I'm not remembering. תוספות Tosafot has an interesting way of splitting of
splitting the two peep... oh, right, I think that's coming up later.
I'm sorry, that's coming up later, not this case. Okay. So if
it's your own ox, you obviously don't have any financial liability, but
you get lashes. If it's somebody else's ox, then you have two
things going on here. have both lashes for transgressing and you have
the financial liability for the person's ox had a rice for lunch.
So the גמרא Gemara says, but you don't get both. You normally
don't allow a person to both for the same act, both get
lashes and to pay money. So how is this happening in this
case?
והא אין לוקה ומשלם? v'ha ein loke u'meshalem? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הא מני רבי מאיר היא, ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi, דאמר לוקה ומשלם. d'amar loke u'meshalem. No, there's a
position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir by עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim that
says עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim get lashes and they also for testifying
falsely and they also have to pay if they would have said
that somebody had to pay, right, they were falsely testifying somebody had
to pay, so ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם, v'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, they
actually go ahead and they pay what they would have made the
other person pay, but they also get lashes for transgressing the prohibition
of testifying falsely. So this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir allows both to happen. So here you get lashes because
you muzzled the ox and you pay the owner for robbing his
ox of lunch. You can extrapolate from עדים זוממים? Eidim Zomemim? So
תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion how you can extrapolate, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara assumes. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now, רבא Rava
has a great answer that occurs at a couple of גמרות, Gemarot,
we've seen it before in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, אתנן אשה ואפילו
בעל אמו. Esnan isha v'afilu ba'al imo. This has got to be
one of those great distilled, like compact, you know, statements that packs
a punch. It says the תורה Torah forbids gifts to prostitutes even
if a man has sex with his mother. Well, that answers that
question. Let's move on. Now, now it makes total sense. So what
the point is is the following. A gift to a prostitute, a
gift, a payment to a prostitute cannot be brought as a קרבן.
korban. Somebody gives a prostitute a sheep, she can't bring it as
a קרבן. korban. Let's say, right, let's say the prostitute happens to
be this man's mother. Okay, so in that act of sex, he
has now been חייב chayav like מיתה, misa, right, he did this
biblical prohibition. Okay, so
therefore, let's say he does it, he got away with it, there
were no witnesses, and then he gave her this sheep as payment.
So do we say that he has no liability, no, he doesn't
owe her anything because of קים ליה kim leh and therefore the
sheep is just a gift and if it's just a gift it
can be brought as a קרבן? korban? Or do we say no,
even though he is exempt because of the principle of קים ליה
kim leh of paying her her fee, okay, if he does pay
it to her, it still constitutes her fee and it still is
a fee of a prostitute and cannot be brought as a קרבן?
korban? So that's what רבא Rava says. When the תורה Torah says
you cannot bring a gift to a prostitute, it doesn't distinguish, even
if the man had sex with his mother. So what does that
teach you? It teaches you that even though we say קים ליה,
kim leh, it does not mean that there is no liability left
afterwards. The way רש"י Rashi frames it is: we as the court
cannot make the person pay. קים ליה Kim leh means we as
the court have our hands tied. If we're already punishing him in
one way, if we're already or prepared to punish him, if there
had been witnesses, we would have given him lashes, we would have
executed him, then we cannot do the lesser punishment, but that doesn't
mean he doesn't owe the money, okay? It just means that we
can't do anything about it. So if he goes ahead and decides
to pay her her fee, it's not a gift; he really does
owe it to her. We won't be able to take that money
from him in court, okay? We can't sort of act on that,
but the debt is really there. And therefore if he gives it,
it's framed as payment and not as a gift. Okay, so here
too, even if רש"י Rashi says we're going to change what the
משנה Mishna means, it doesn't mean we will make this person, we'll
give the person lashes for muzzling the ox and make him pay,
we can't make him pay, there is a principle of קים ליה,
kim leh, but he should pay. He even though there's קים ליה
kim leh he still does owe the money, it's just we can't
act on it. And therefore the תוספות Tosafot even says that's the
language of ומשלם, u'meshalem, and he does pay. It's not ישלם, yeshalem,
he must pay; we won't enforce it, but ideally he should pay.
And actually, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot has the
words בבא לצאת ידי שמים, b'va latzet yedei Shamayim, those words aren't
in our גמרא, Gemara, but apparently in the ב"ח Bach says this,
apparently תוספות, Tosafot, there was a גרסא girsa out there that רבא's
Rava's statement about the gift of a prostitute was preceded by the
words: we're talking about בבא לצאת ידי שמים. b'va latzet yedei Shamayim.
We're not talking about somebody who can be forced to pay; we're
talking about somebody who is trying to do the right thing. And
if you want
to do the right thing and fulfill your obligation even though the
court won't act on it, then you still have to pay, like
this principle we learned from the case of the prostitute. Then even
if you say קים ליה, kim leh, the liability is still there.
Now, in the prostitute case he still owes her the money and
if he gives it to her it's defined as an אתנן. esnan.
And in this case, he owes the owner of the ox the
money for what the ox would have eaten, even if as a
court we won't make him pay. Now, it is interesting to ask,
you know, is this idea that there is still a liability even
after קים ליה kim leh true in all cases of monetary payment?
There's something unique about this case. Imagine for example that I went
ahead and the רש"י Rashi says like I shot an arrow at
a guy and it killed him and it ripped his shirt in
the process. Okay, would you say there as well that I have
a liability to pay let's say בידי שמים bidei shamayim because of
the damage? So maybe yes, maybe it's the same principle, you know,
that liability is there even after קים ליה Kim lei but it
could be we understand it differently. It could be that this case
is a punishment, meaning this case, excuse me, is the monetary obligation
is not a type of a punishment, the monetary obligation is actually
a contractual obligation, right? The reason, the reason that this person is
paying is because the reason, the reason that this person is paying
is because what do you call it? I'm sorry, I'm just losing
my train of thought here. The reason this person is paying in
the both the case by the case of the mother and the
prostitute and the case here of the ox is because not some
type of a of a tort, but because of some type of
a contractual obligation. He agreed to pay the prostitute. He, when he
took this ox, he was effectively agreeing to allow the ox to
eat. So, it's very interesting question. Should a contractual obligation not be
enforceable just because the liability came at the time where there was
some court-imposed punishment like lashes or execution? Right? I think it's very
different to think of an idea of קים ליה Kim lei when
we're dealing with a question of like to impose a tort, to
make you pay for מזיק mazzik or certainly a fine, and we're
not going to do that at the same time we're going to
do lashes or death penalty. But as opposed to something like this,
which is an obligation that's due to a contractual agreement. So, it's
not so clear to me that that should be, you know, that
קים ליה Kim lei should have the same effect. So in the
two cases that גמרא's Gemara applying this idea of אתנן זונה ואפילו
בעל אמו, Esnan Zona v'Afilu Baal Imo, right? One of them is
what do you call it? One of them is a case, they're
both cases of contractual agreements. So it could be that דוקא davka
in those cases are ones where there still is a sense of
liability, maybe won't make force the person to pay, but a sense
of liability even in even after קים ליה, Kim lei, yes. Is
one of the issue the language that is used in ספר דברים
Sefer Devarim about paying a prostitute is kind of strange, it's it's
about bringing the it's about Okay, but I don't want to go
there now. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב פפא
Amar Rav Papa anyways, that's answer number two. Answer number one was
it's goes like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, answer number two was it's
still you still have a sort of an obligation, you know, to
the owner and to Heaven and so on, even if the court
won't impose it. And let's see what the next answer is. רב
פפא אמר משעת משיכה חייב ליה במזונותיה. Rav Papa Amar Mishas Meshicha
chayiv lei b'mezonoteha.
From the time of he tries to separate the moment of the
liability of payment and the liability for lashes. When you took the
guy's cow and you were renting the guy's cow, okay, you became
liable to feed it. And part of the feeding of the cow
was meaning you were going to let it eat while it was
doing the work. So your liability to feed it began at that
moment. And then you didn't satisfy it, that liability, because you muzzled
it while it was doing the threshing, okay. ומלקא לא לקי עד
שעת חסימה, Umalka la lalki ad shas chasima,
but the lashes are for the muzzling. But because you muzzled, you're
liable for the obligation you assumed when you first took the cow.
And therefore, you're able to pay both because they're not coming at
the same time. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, said Rav Papa,
הני מילי בעי מינאי דבי רב פפא בר אבא... hanni milei bo'ei
minai d'vei Rav Papa bar Abba... okay, so
so the following sort of questions were asked from me, בעי מינאי
דבי רב פפא בר אבא, bo'ei minai d'vei Rav Papa bar Abba,
in the house of Rav Papa bar Abba... is he talking about
his own house? How'd I translate this sentence? It's the academy of
Rav Papa's father. Oh, it's a dilemma entered by the house of
Rav Papa bar Abba. It's a different house than the same Rav
Papa. Okay, so interesting, it's two Rav Papas, anyway. All right, said
Rav Papa, okay, the anyway what does Steinzaltz say? דערמיילע שאלו אותי
בני ביתו של רב פפא בר אבא. Darmaileh sha'alu osi bnei beiso
shel Rav Papa bar Abba. I guess he's a different Rav Papa.
Okay, fine. Anyway, אמר רב פפא: הני מילי בעי מינאי דבי רב
פפא בר אבא. Amar Rav Papa: hanni milei bo'ei minai d'vei Rav
Papa bar Abba. The following things were asked from me from the
house of Rav Papa bar Abba, ופשטי להו לאיסורא. upashki lehu l'issura.
And I concluded for them that both of their questions, the answer
was אסור. assur. Okay, they asked me two הלכה halacha questions, I
said אסור assur to both. חדא כהלכתא וחדא לאו כהלכתא. Chada k'hilchasa
v'chada lav k'hilchasa. One of them that the הלכה halacha really was
that it was אסור. assur. The other the הלכה halacha really was
that it was מותר, mutar, but I was being extra strict. Okay,
what were the two things? בעי מינאי, Bo'ei minai, they asked from
me, מהו ללוש את העיסה בחלב? mahu l'lush es ha'issa b'chalav? Are
you allowed to make dough, milk bread? Are you allowed to make
dough with milk? ופשטי להו לאיסורא, Upashki lehu l'issura, I told them
that you're not allowed to, it's forbidden. The bread is forbidden. כהלכתא,
K'hilchasa, that's the הלכה, halacha, this really is the הלכה halacha that
you're not allowed to have milk bread. דתניא, D'tanya, which we learned
in a ברייתא, Baraisa, אין לשין את העיסה בחלב, ein lashin es
ha'issa b'chalav, you're not allowed to make dough with with milk. ואם
לש, V'im lash, and if you do, כל הפת כלה אסורה, kol
hapas kullah asurah, the whole bread is forbidden. מפני הרגל עבירה, Mipnei
hergel aveira, because it'll lead to a sin. Why it'll lead to
a sin? Because you eat bread with every meal and therefore if
you have milk bread, you'll eat it with פליישיגס, fleishigs, and therefore
the whole bread is forbidden. Now it's allowed if you have a
certain סימן siman on the bread. There are questions what if you
have a סימן siman exterior to the bread, like if your packaging
says OU. but there's no סימן siman on the bread itself? Okay,
so exactly. Anyway, but that's the הלכה. halacha. The details are debated.
Okay. כיוצא בסימולה, kiotze bosimula, אין תשמיש התורה בעליה, ein tashmesh hatorah
be'alyah, you cannot smear with a fat tail the oven, right to
I don't know what it does, it helps maybe lock in the
heat or something like that. Apparently this though is a fat tail
of a כשר kosher animal that was שחט shechted properly, but the
point is that it's פליישיג. fleishig. ואם עשה, ve'im asa, כל הפת
כולה אסורה, kol hapat kula asura, and if you did it, any
bread baked in that oven would be forbidden. Not just it'd be
פליישיג, fleishig, it'd be forbidden. עד שיסיק את התנור ad sheyaseki et
hatanur until you fire up the oven to remove all of the
grease. Okay, so that's the הלכה halacha of that מילכיג milchig bread
and פליישיג fleishig bread are אסור, assur, even to eat by themselves.
ואידך בעו מיניה, ve'idach ba'u minei, the other thing they asked him,
מהו להכניס מין ושאינו מינו לדיר. ma'u lehachnis min vesheno mino ladir.
Can you bring, this is why it's relevant because we're talking about
חוסם chosem the mouth of an ox and we're talking about cross
breeding. So are you allowed to not actually do the physical act
of, you know, of cross breeding, but to make the cross breeding
happen? You bring like, you know, I don't know an two different
species into the same barn and you lock the barn and you
hope that they cross breed. I mean I don't know if that
would ever happen if somebody wasn't forcing it. But anyway, okay, ופשטיהו
לאיסורא, upashtihu le'issura, and I told them it was forbidden. דלאו כהלכתא
de-lav ke-hilchata and that's really not the הלכה halacha I was just
being extra strict. דאמר שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says, במנאפין עד
שיהיו כדרך המנאפים, benafin ad sheyehu kederach hamenafim, if you want to
have עדים aidim testify that people committed a sin of forbidden sexual
act whether it was adultery or incest or whatever, you actually have
to see them not just in bed together and acting in ways
in which you can infer that they're having intercourse, but you actually
have to directly witness the act of intercourse itself. The image used
is like well here I'm sorry I misstated that. That's the next
point, he במנאפין כדרך המנאפים, benafin kederach hamenafim, okay this actually debated,
okay. כדרך המנאפים kederach hamenafim means they look like adulterers, meaning they're
going at it and you know and all the actions you know
make it very clear what's happening but you don't actually see the
genitals. Okay but you sort of see everything else and it's you
know you could pretty likely infer what's happening but you didn't actually
see the act of intercourse. Okay is that enough? That's דרך מנאפים.
derech menafim. The contrast to דרך מנאפים derech menafim is כמכחול בשפופרת,
kemichol bashfopheres, which you're about to say, which is sort of like
an eyelash applicator into the tube. Okay which is basically a way
of saying to get that image in your head, a way of
saying to directly see the act of intercourse. So that's the question,
right, would you need to directly see it or is it enough
to see כדרך המנאפים? kederach hamenafim? So he says במנאפין עד שיהיו
כדרך המנאפים, benafin ad sheyehu kederach hamenafim, when it comes to testifying
adultery you don't have to see the act of intercourse, you just
have to sort of see them acting as you know in ways
you see their bodies and it's indicates that they're having intercourse, okay,
ובכלאים עד שיכניס כמכחול בשפופרת, ubekilayim ad sheyachnis kemichol bashfopheres, but to
transgress the prohibition of crossbreeding, you actually have to insert, you know,
the you know the male genital, you know, the penis into the
vagina. You actually have to handle the actual genitals themselves like the
eyelash applicator into the tube. Okay and until you do that, you
know, you have not transgressed the biblical prohibition of crossbreeding. Okay so
מתיב רב אחדבוי בר אמי. mativ Rav Achdevoy bar Ami. So anyway
but I told them it was אסור. assur. Even though technically it's
allowed, I told them they shouldn't do it because like it's not
proper. Now, מתיב רב אחדבוי בר אמי, mativ Rav Achdevoy bar Ami,
אילו נאמר בהם בהמתך לא תרביע, ilu ne'emar bahem behemtcha lo tarbia,
had it not had the word כלאים kilayim had it just said
don't crossbreed your don't breed your animals without the word כלאים kilayim
it just means don't breed your animals, הייתי אומר לא יאחוז אדם
בבהמה בשעה שעולה עליה זכר, hayisi omer lo yochoz adam babehema besha'at
she'olah aleha zachar, that you can't even be participating in the natural
breeding of your animals if it had not had the word כלאים.
kilayim. Don't hold the female while the male is mounting her. תלמוד
לומר כלאים, talmud lomar kilayim. it says no no no the problem
is not being involved in the breeding, the problem is breeding them
interbreeding them. Okay so what but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara says, but
we're describing the act that you're doing as not directly manipulating the
genitals. So if that's true what how we're describing the act then
presumably the prohibition of כלאים kilayim, is even without directly manipulating. רב
מכלל דבכלאים אחיזה נמי לא? Rav miklal debekilayim achiza nami lo? Doesn't
this imply that to transgress כלאים kilayim even just holding the animals
to make them do it, to allow them do it, you would
transgress? Okay, so maybe not putting them in a barn but maybe
holding them during the act that would be considered a transgression? לא,
lo, no, מאי אחיזה הכנסה, mai achiza hachnasa, when this ברייתא braisa
says speaks about holding the animal, we really mean directly inserting the
genitals. So if that's true אמאי קרי ליה אחיזה? amay karei lei
achiza? So why does it describe it as holding the animals? לישנא
מעליא, lishna ma'alya, we're being a little euphemistic. Okay but technically speaking
you are you do not transgress even if you are holding the
animals at the moment of the act if you do not directly
manipulate the genitals, which is pretty surprising. But okay. אמר רב יהודה,
amar Rav Yehuda, מין במינו, min bemino, now we're talking about כלאים,
kilayim מין במינו מותר להכניס כמכחול בשפופרת. min bemino mutar lehachnis kemichol
bashfopheres. Let's say you're a farmer there and you're really trying to
breed your animals not interbreed them to breed them, you are allowed
to actually since it's מין במינו min bemino it's the same type
of species, you're allowed to actually breed them and directly manipulating the
genitals like putting the eyelash applicator into the tube. applicator into the
tube. ואפילו משום פריצותא ליכא. ve'afilu mishum pritzuta lekka. So and it's
not even a problem of like licentious behavior, like you know directly
handling genitals of the animals, directly being involved in this act of
intercourse. מאי טעמא בעבידתי טריד. Mai ta'ama ba'avidtei tarid. Look, this is
your job, okay? So it does not provoke sexual thoughts. רב אחדבוי
בר אמי. Rav Achdaboi bar Ami. Now רב אחדבוי בר אמי, Rav
Achdaboi bar Ami, we're still going to question this question about what
constitutes the act of כלאים. kilayim, Had it just said בהמתך לא
תרביע, behemtecha lo tarbi'a, do not breed your animals without the word
כלאים, kilayim. הייתי אומר לא יאחוז אדם את הבהמה כדי שיעלה הזכר,
haiti omer lo yo'cheiz adam et habehemah kedei she'ya'aleh hazachar, that you
can't even be involved in the breeding of the same species. Don't
hold the animal when the male mounts it. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar
כלאים. kilayim, כלאים הוא דאסר, kilayim hu de'asar, כלאים kilayim is forbidden.
המין במינו שרי, hamin be'mino sharei, but the same species is permissible.
So now we, yeah, well let me just finish this. So the
גמרא Gemara says, but again it's the same question. Does it use
the phrase holding and not direct manipulating? So the גמרא Gemara says,
ומין במינו נמי אחיזה אין הכנסה לא. umin be'mino nami achiza in
hachnasa lo. Only thing that's allowed is holding them. So it's the
same question except before we were asking it from the כלאים kilayim
perspective and here we're asking it from the מין במינו min be'mino
perspective. You told me that מין במינו min be'mino is not a
problem of licentious behavior to directly manipulate the genitals. This ברייתא braita
discusses only holding the animals not being a problem. It doesn't discuss
directly manipulating the genitals. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי אחיזה
הכנסה. mai achiza hachnasa. When this ברייתא braita says it's okay if
it's the same species to hold it, it doesn't just mean holding
it, it means even directly inserting. ואמאי קרי ליה אחיזה? ve'amai karei
leh achiza? So then why was it called holding? לישנא מעליא, lishna
ma'alya, just to speak in nice euphemistic terms. But which is funny
because it is הלכה, halacha, you want to be more precise, but
anyway that's what at least this position is saying is that it
is permissible to directly manipulate the genitals of the same species and
of different species you don't transgress until you directly manipulate the genitals.
Yes, Rabbi Dov you had a question. Yeah, so is the concern
of פריצות? pritzut? Is the concern to not become precariously close, not
to have sexual thoughts? Primarily. Not to jump and be the third
in the bargain? No, no, no, the question is sexual thoughts. תרביע,
tarbi'a, right? It's even though... I understand, but that's certainly not how...
maybe. רש"י Rashi says it's sexual thoughts. Yeah, that's how רש"י Rashi
understands. בעי מיניה דרב אשי. ba'ei mineih de'Rav Ashi. So the following
question was asked from רב אשי. Rav Ashi. I'm sorry, אמר רב
אשי, amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי. Rav Ashi. הא מילתא בעי
מיניה דבי רב נחמיה ריש גלותא. ha milta ba'ei mineih de'bei Rav
Nechemiah Reish Galuta. The following thing was asked from me from the
house of נחמיה Nechemiah of of רב נחמיה Rav Nechemiah of the
ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. מהו להכניס מין ומינו ושאינו מינו לדיר? mahu
le'hachnis min umino veshe'eino mino le'diyar? Here, here Rabbi Dov we have
three of them. Okay can you put in two same animal species
and a third one into the same you know into the same
barn and lock the door? Now that assumes that just one of
each type would be forbidden,
which we said before was not the real הלכה. halacha. But this
sort of assuming, well maybe that's inappropriate one of each type but
how about two and one? So what do we say? כיון דאיכא
מיניה בתר מיניה גריר. keivan de'ika mineih batar mineih garir. Since the
you know the cow there has a bull it'll stick with the
bull, it won't go to the other species. או דילמא אפילו הכי
לא? od dilma afilu hachi lo? Or even maybe even so we
shouldn't put it in together with another species. ופשט ליה לאיסורא. upashat
leh le'issura. And he concluded that it was forbidden. דלא כהלכתא. d'lo
ke'hilchata. But that's not the real הלכה. halacha. The same way מין
ומינו min umino isn't really the הלכה halacha but we were being
strict. Here too wasn't the real הלכה halacha but we were being
strict. Why? משום פריצותא דעבדי. mishum pritzuta de'avdei. That's just you know,
it's like licentious, I don't know, anyway somehow it's improper. So halachically
you can put, you don't transgress and you can put them in
the same barn, but for these safeguard reasons, more פריצותא pritzuta concerns,
you shouldn't even put two of one species in a third of
another. Okay let's go on to the next משנה, mishna, back to
the issue of חסימה chasima or the worker's rights to eat. היה
עושה בידיו אבל לא ברגליו. haya oseh beyadav aval lo beraglav. Let's
say a worker was working and he was only working with his
hands and not with his feet. או ברגליו אבל לא בידיו, o
beraglav aval lo beyadav, or with his feet but not with his
hands, okay. אפילו בכתפו, afilu bichtefo, or even if he was working
just with his shoulder, now I don't know, I mean because you're
schlepping something I guess you're working with your shoulder and your feet,
but I don't know, maybe you're just holding something steady while somebody
else is you know you're holding up a bucket while somebody else
is taking from it or something. הרי זה אוכל. harei zeh ochel.
You're allowed to eat, okay, because you're working. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר עד שיעשה בידיו וברגליו. Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda omer ad she'ya'aseh
beyadav u'veraglav. You're not allowed to eat until you're working both with
your hands and your feet, okay? So if you're picking grapes, I
mean you know you're moving through the vineyard and you're picking. You
don't have to use your hands and your feet simultaneously, but it
sort of involves both parts of your body. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
What's the reason of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that it doesn't
matter how you're doing the work? כי תבוא בכרם רעך, ki tavo
b'kerem rei'echa, when you come into your friend's vineyard, בכל מאי דעביד,
bechol mai de'avid, however you're working in the vineyard, why should we
limit it? ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר עד שיעשה בידיו וברגליו. ve'Rabbi
Yose berabbi Yehuda omer ad she'ya'aseh beyadav u'veraglav. No, you have to
use your hands and feet. מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? Mai
ta'ama de'Rabbi Yose berabbi Yehuda? כי שור, ki shor, like an ox,
because we've been linking the ox to the human, right, in terms
of these ideas of their right to eat. מה שור עד שיעשה
בידיו וברגליו. ma shor ad she'ya'aseh beyadav u'veraglav. An ox doesn't have
hands and feet, but okay. אף פועל עד שיעשה בידו וברגלו. af
po'el ad she ya'aseh beyadov u'veraglov. So you too, you have to
use both your hands and your feet and otherwise you're not entitled
to eat. בעי רבא בר בר רב הונא. Ba'ei Rava bar bar
Rav Huna. So Rava bar bar Rav Huna asked, דש באווזין ותרנגולים
לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מהו. dash be'avazin ve'tarnigolin le'Rabbi Yosi berbi Yehuda
mahu. Let's say according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosi berbi
Yehuda that they need your hands and your feet, let's say an
animal doesn't have hands. Let's say you were using ducks and chickens
to do your threshing. It'd be a very interesting threshing, very ineffective
one I would imagine if you were doing it with ducks and
chickens, but anyway, okay, but it doesn't have any hands, okay? So
what would be the הלכה? halakha? לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מהו? le'Rabbi
Yosi berbi Yehuda mahu? בכל כוחו בעינן? bekhol kokho ba'inan? Does he
really mean hands and feet or does he mean using like all
of your, you know, put all your body into it? So in
this case the animal is putting all of its body into it.
ואיכא. ve'ika. או דילמא בידו וברגלו בעינן. o dilma beyadov u'veraglov ba'inan.
No, technically it's hands and feet. וליכא, ve'leika, and you don't have
it. תיקו. teiku. So the גמרא Gemara says we don't know. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar
Avuha, פועלים, po'alim, let's say you have workers that are stomping on
grapes—presumably they're talking about this because that's a classic example of using
your feet, okay?—they're stomping on grapes, so they're allowed to eat. Now
we're about to see in the next משנה mishna that you're only
allowed to eat from the thing you're doing the work with. If
you're going and picking apples and there's a pear tree nearby, you
can't pick from the pear. Also, if you're working in wine, you
can't eat from the grapes, and if you're working in grapes, you
can't eat from the wine. Let's say you're stomping grapes, so you're
working with grapes and wine, so you can eat from the grapes
and the wine. But here at what stage? So until you've gone
שתי וערב, sheti va'erev, like you know, horizontal and vertical, back and,
you know, back in both directions on the grape in the vat,
you're considered at that stage to only be working with the grapes.
אוכלין ענבים ואין שותין יין. okhlin anavim ve'ein shotim yayin. You cannot
yet drink from any of the wine because you have not yet
the wine is not yet begun to flow. Maybe it means that
even if the other workers, the wine is already flowing, because if
you want to eat from the wine it must be flowing. But
even if the wine is flowing because of what the other workers
did, right, I mean I guess it's a question—I don't know—is it
a question whether you're yet considered to be working with the wine?
So until you've done a certain degree of stomping, you're only working
with the grapes. משיחלכו שתי וערב, misheyahal'khu sheti va'erev, once you've gone,
you know, both directions in the vat, in that case אוכלין ענבים
ושותין יין, okhlin anavim ve'shotin yayin, then you're working both with grapes
and with wine. Even though your job is to get the wine
out of the grapes, you're not really doing anything with the wine,
but nevertheless it's considered that you're working with the wine and therefore
you are allowed to, okay? So now we go on to exactly
that הלכה halakha in the next משנה. mishna. היה עושה בתאנים לא
יאכל בענבים. Haya oseh be'te'enim lo yokhal be'anavim. If you're working with
with figs, don't eat grapes. בענבים לא יאכל בתאנים, ba'anavim lo yokhal
be'te'enim, grapes don't eat figs. אבל מונע את עצמו, Aval mone'a et
atzmo, even though you're allowed to eat you can't, you know, eat
something else, you can choose not to eat the grapes that are
right in front of you עד שיגיע למקום יפה, ad she'yagi'a limkom
yafeh, until you get to the place in the vineyard where the
grapes are very good, okay? So you can choose when you're going
to eat those grapes. ואוכל, ve'okhal, and then you can eat. וכולן
לא אמרו אלא בשעת מלאכה. Ve'kulan lo amru ela besha'at melakha. Now
all of the time you're allowed to eat is only while you're
doing the work. אבל משום השב אבידה לבעלים, Aval mishum hashev aveida
le've'alim, but in order to return lost objects to the owners—we'll see
what that means, but basically to save the owners the time of
the workers—אמרו פועלים אוכלין בהליכתן מאומן לאומן. amru po'alim okhlin behalikhatan me'uman
le'uman. The פועלים po'alim can eat when they go from one row
to the next row. ובחזירתן מן הגת, U've'khaziratan min hagat, and when
they return from the threshing floor, because imagine what's going to happen,
right? So you're telling me that that I can only eat while
I'm working and I can only like, you know, and I can
wait though till I get to the good grapes. So I'm going
to go through this sort of row and then I'm going to
sort of stop here at the end of the row where the
grapes are good. I'm going to eat here, okay? And I'm not
going to be, you know, and I'm going to take my time,
right? I'm going to eat a grape and then put some grapes
into the bucket, eat a grape, put some grapes into the bucket
because as soon as I leave this row I'm not going to
be able to continue to eat the grapes. Right? If I move
these grapes and as I'm walking over to the next row, I
won't be able to eat because I'm not doing מלאכה. melakha. So
what they actually said is, you know what? Better for the owner,
for the sake of the owner's time, that what they're going to
let me do is grab a bunch of grapes and then eat
them as I'm walking to the next row. Okay? So that's technically
not שעת מלאכה, sha'at melakha, okay? Or when I'm returning back from
the, you know, from the threshing floor, okay? You know, grab some
grapes and eat them on my way back, right? So then I'm
not taking away any of the owner's time. So technically I'm not
allowed to eat, but it's better that, you know, I'm not stopping
my work, but it's actually it's the best, it's actually for this
is the owner would prefer. Eat it when you're not when it's
not going to be distracting you from your work, okay? So that
actually is what what we have structured it, even though that's not
technically when the person is allowed. ובחמור כשהיא פורקת, U'vakhamor keshe'hi poreket,
and in a donkey, now, a donkey can eat when it is
unburdened or or, you know, as it's being unburdened. We'll see what
that means in the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Now they
ask the following question. עושה בגפן זהו מהו שיאכל בגפן אחר? Oseh
be'gefen zehu mahu she'yokhal be'gefen acher? Let's say I'm eating off of
vine A, I'm working on vine A, I'm plucking the grapes from
vine A and right next to vine A is vine B. Can
I eat the grapes from vine B? Okay, it's still the same
vineyard, it's all grapes, but it's not the exact vine that I'm
working on. Okay, so what do we say? ממי שאתה נותן לכליו
של בעל הבית בעינן? mi'mi she'atah noten la'kelav she'ba'al habayit ba'inan? Do
you just need it to be the same type of food that
you're putting into that you're gathering is the one that you can
eat? And then הא איכא ha ika and you have that? או
דלמא o dilma ממה שאתה נותן לכליו של בעל הבית, mimah she'atah
noten la'kelav she'ba'al habayit, from the thing that you are harvesting, from
that physical thing itself, that's the thing you can eat from? והא
ליכא ve'ha lika and you're not, and that's you're not, you're not
taking from the vine that you're harvesting, you're taking from a from
a different vine. ואם תמצי לומר ve'im timtzi lomar עושה בגפן זה
לא יאכל בגפן אחר, oseh b'gefen zeh lo yochal b'gefen acher, if
we were to say that you can't do it, you cannot take
from a different vine, it has to be from the vine itself,
so then you might ask the following question: שור במחובר היכי אכיל?
shor b'mechubar heichi achil? How does an ox ever eat when it
is threshing when it is working? Because an ox eats when it's
threshing, that's the case in the תורה. Torah. But we also learn
from the worker that an ox eats when it is doing work
on standing grain, right? So imagine you've got an ox here, right?
Now you ever see those things where they have this ox and
it's like carrying what is it, some type of a thing that
it's like threshing with? Right? I don't know. Anyway, behind the ox
it's pulling some type of a thing that's like threshing the grain,
right? So the ox is eating from the grain here, right? So
if you have to eat from the same thing you're doing the
work on, so how can an ox ever eat from attached? Right?
When it's threshing, all the stuff it's working on is underneath its
feet and it can be eating from the thing itself. But here
it's doing the work on one thing and its mouth is elsewhere.
So how would you ever have that case if it would have
to be the same physical object? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי amar Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi בסיכא
b'sircha או בשתכא o b'shatcha whatever, which basically means we're dealing with
some very long type of a thing. So רש"י Rashi says it
means, so you basically, I mean it doesn't work with it doesn't
work with grain, but if you basically imagine a vine, okay, you
could have some type of a case where you could have a
vine that's going like this, right? And there's a grape here, and
somehow I don't know what they're doing, maybe what the work the
ox is doing is he's he's carrying like a carriage and the
workers are picking the grapes, right, off of the vine and putting
them into into some type of a wagon that the ox is
carrying. So the ox is doing the work here, right, on this
vine, he's sort of carrying the wagon that the workers are using
to load it up and it's a very long vine and he's
able to eat from the grape at the head of the vine.
So that would be the case if you needed it to be
the same actual like thing, not just the same species, but the
same thing that you can eat from is the one that you're
doing the work on. So what's the הלכה? halacha? תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear. היה עושה בתאנים לא יאכל בענבים, hayah oseh
bi'te'enim lo yochal ba'anavim, if you're dealing with figs, don't eat from
grapes. הא תאנים ותאנים, ha te'enim ve'te'enim, if you're dealing with figs,
figs and figs, דומיא דתאנים וענבים dumya d'te'enim va'anavim parallel to figs
and grapes, אוכל, ochal, this is actually quite a good proof. Right?
Figs and grapes are obviously from two different sources and the only
problem with it is that they're different species. Which would mean that
if it's two different sources and the same thing, figs and figs
or grapes and grapes, it should be okay. Right? ואי אמרת ve'i
amrat עושה בגפן זה אינו אוכל בגפן אחר, oseh b'gefen zeh eino
ochal b'gefen acher, if you're dealing with one you can't eat in
another, so היכי משכחת לה, heichi mashkachat lah, so how would you
ever have a case of grapes and grapes similar to grapes and
figs? Grapes and figs are obviously two different sources. So אמר רב
ששת בריה דרב אידי amar Rav Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi במודלית. b'mudles.
We're talking about a case of a of a vine that is
basically wrapped around a tree. Okay, so let's not worry about כלאים
kilayim right now, but here you've got your tree, right? Here you
got your figs and here you've got your grape vine. Okay? So
in this type of a case, okay, you are this is when
you can't eat grapes and figs, but they're essentially one thing. Now
the question is why? I mean, if if you still need it
to be from the same source, okay, so if I have one
grape vine like this and one grape vine like this and even
if they're like intertwined, right? Let's even imagine that. Right? I mean
here, let's use different colors.
So here's one grape vine.
Do some like sine curves. And here's another grape vine. Okay, and
they're intertwined. Okay, let's even assume they're intertwined. If the הלכה halacha
is I can only eat from the thing I'm doing the work
on, so so what? While I'm picking the black grapes, I'm not
doing the work on the purple. So even if they're physically intertwined,
right? Why should I be able to eat from the other one?
I'm only in and you could say, well, I'm picking from both,
so maybe the גמרא Gemara is talking that you're picking from both
simultaneously or something. But still that's not similar, here you're only doing
work with one. So what רש"י Rashi explains is the following: you
might only be trying to pick right now the black grapes, but
in order to get access to the black grapes, and I'm not
saying they're physically actually black, but for all purposes, you have to
you have to remove, you have to handle the other vine. You
have to get the other vine out of the way. So actually
in this case you're only doing work with this, but because you're
handling both vines, you're allowed to actually take. Take the grapes from
the other vine. Okay, so in that case, if this was a
different species, you wouldn't. But yes, is it possible you could eat
from a different source than the one you are? Maybe. But maybe
that would only yes, but that would only maybe that would only
be in a case when you're actually handling that other source, not
when you're not handling it. And why distinguish between two different varieties?
Because if they were two different varieties, you wouldn't be able to.
Yeah, why? Well, that's the הלכה halacha that, you know, because they
they learn from, I mean, the גמרא gemara doesn't say, but it
learns from the פסוק pasuk presumably, כי תבא בכרם רעך ואכלת ענבים.
Ki Tavo Bekarmei Re'echa Ve'achalta Anavim. Like you have to keep to
the same thing that you're eating. That's just discern from the context.
And also you're being asked to work with those? No, because you're
not picking. See, that's what רש״י Rashi says. If you had to,
let's say, move this out of the way to get access to
this, your job is still only on this. So you're not entitled
to eat the grapes.
Okay, well, that's the הלכה. halacha. You know, if this is your
only, your only job is to move it out of the way.
Right, so that's part of the חידוש chiddush here, you know, that
it's not enough to be handling it, you have to be harvesting
from it. So in this case, if you're only harvesting from this,
you don't have a right even if you're handling here, you're even
if you're only harvesting from the black. It's true, I understand the
grapes, but keep your hands off my figs. Yeah, but I do
understand the logical issue here. Yeah, this is all academic because it's
all going to be prohibited because of כלאים. kilayim. No, not necessarily.
It depends on various other things, so we're not going to worry
about that. Okay, תא שמע. ta shma. Okay, so now we still
have an open question. I agree with Dov's point, which is it's
a little bit strange, right? If what, like make up your mind,
like if the הלכה halacha is that you're considered to be working
with the thing that you have to move out of the way,
then it shouldn't matter if it's a different species, and if you're
not working with it, why are you allowed to eat from it
if it's the same species? But anyway, that's how the גמרא gemara
solves this problem. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, come in here, אבל
המונע עצמו עד שמגיע למקום היפה ואוכל. aval amone'a atzmo ad shemagi'a
lemakom hayafeh ve'ochel. You can hold yourself back until you get to
the good part of the vine and eat from those grapes. ואם
אמרת עושה בגפן זה ואוכל בגפן אחר. ve'im amarta oseh begefen zeh
ve'ochel begefen acher. But the גמרא gemara says, well, but then but
there's a but why do you have to do that? There's a
much better solution, right? Why should you like wait until you get
to the head of the vine and do all your eating there?
I got a way that you can do your eating wherever you
want. Why?
ניזיל וניתי וניכול. neizil unaitai veniichol. Here you are, you're in the
middle of the vine, so what you should do is run to
the head of the vine, grab a big cluster of grapes, come
back to where you are, do your work here, and you know,
eat from the grapes here while you're working in another part of,
you know, back here in the row. So clearly the reason you're
not allowed to is because you're only allowed to eat from the
grapes that are immediately in front of you, or the גמרא gemara
now you could say there's a difference between in front of you
and from literally the same vine. That's what I would have said.
I would have imagined that what the תורה Torah is doing is
letting you sort of do from the stuff that's sort of like
שור בדישך, shor be'dishecha, you see the stuff immediately around you you're
allowed, you can't go run somewhere else and take it. But immediately
around you is a different you know גמרא gemara sort of assumes
very narrowly. No, no, only the same vine. So anyway from here
if it were you see you see that you are limited to
the same vine because if you weren't, why not run to the
run and get some good grapes and bring them back? So the
גמרא gemara says no, התם משום ביטול מלאכה לא קמיבעיא לן. hatam
mishum bitul melacha lo kamibaya lan. That's the reason you can't run
to the head of the vine is because you're leaving your job.
Right, כי קמיבעיא לן היכא דאיכא אשתו ובניו. ki kamibaya lan heicha
de'ika ishto uvanav. Our question would be that you got your wife
and your kids with you and you want to send them to
the head of the vine and bring it back. You're not leaving
your job. Are you allowed to do that? But again, it is
interesting that the גמרא gemara is not distinguishing between the issue of
the same vine as opposed to your immediate sort of environs, which
I could still see. תא שמע, ta shma, come in here. וכולם
לא אמרו אלא בשעת מלאכה. vekulam lo amru ella besha'at melacha. Oh,
by the way, Dov gets a מזל טוב, mazel tov, he's a
grandfather. מזל
טוב. mazel tov. Alright, sorry I sent you an email, but I
forgot to tell you in person. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, come
in here. וכולם לא אמרו אלא בשעת מלאכה. vekulam lo amru ella
besha'at melacha.
Technically they're only allowed to eat when they're doing the work, אבל
משום השבת אבידה לבעלים, aval mishum hashavat aveidah l'be'alim, but in order
to save time, you know, their workers' time for the owners, אמרו
פועלים אוכלים בהליכתם מאומן לאומן, amru poalim ochlim behalichatam meuman leuman, they
can eat when they go from one row to the next row,
ובחזירתם מן הגת, u'vachaziratam min hagat, when they come back from the
threshing floor. So now סברוה, savru'a, we were assuming מהלך כעושה מעשה
דמי. mehalech k'oseh ma'aseh dami. Here's the question, I said this different
when I read the משנה. mishna. Do we assume that the walking
from one vine to another is considered like you're still doing work
for the owner? Like logically like yeah, if that's part of what
you need to do to do the work, right? So that's the
question, why does the משנה mishna have to say we need a
special condition to let the workers eat when they're going from one
row to the next? Aren't they still doing work from the owner?
Isn't going to the next vine part of working for the owner?
So we're assuming that it is part of working for the owner.
So why do you need a special הלכה? halacha? ומשום השבת אבידה
לבעלים הוא דאכלי, umishum hashavat aveidah l'be'alim hu de'achli, and nevertheless it's
saying that they're only eating because of the special תקנה, takana, מדאורייתא
לא אכלי, mid'oraita lo achli, not biblically. Now why not? אלמא עושה
בגפן זה אינו אוכל בגפן אחר. alma oseh begefen zeh eino ochel
begefen acher. So you see that the problem why we had to
make a special תקנה takana is because if I picked the grapes
at row A and I'm walking over to row B, it's not
like I'm not doing מלאכה melacha now. now, but it's that my
מלאכה melacha is done with row A. And once my מלאכה melacha
is done with row A and my walking is for the sake
of row B, I can't be eating the grapes from row A.
Okay, so if you assume I'm still doing מלאכה, melacha, the only
reason I can't eat is because the grapes were from a different
part of the vineyard than I'm doing מלאכה melacha in right now,
or from a different vine. So doesn't that prove that you cannot
eat from a different vine? Gemara says, no, no, לעולם עושה בגפן
זה אוכל בגפן אחר. le'olam oseh begefen zeh ochel begefen acher. No,
you can eat from a different vine. ומהלך לאו כעושה מעשה דמי,
u'mehalek lav ke'oseh ma'aseh dami, but the חידוש chiddush here is that
walking is not considered doing מלאכה. melacha. Okay, it's necessary, you know,
but it's that's sort of like in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
the question is, you know, is the act of הליכה halicha of
bringing the stuff to the מזבח mizbeach one of the עבודות avodos
of the כהן, kohen, right? How much is just travel? We actually
had it earlier. How much is your travel to and from work
on your time or on the owner's time? Anyway, how much is
this a necessary part of the job or is this the job
itself? So the גמרא Gemara says the reason you need to allow
him to work from going from one row to the next is
not because he can't eat grapes from one part and to a
different part. It's because right at this moment he's not considered to
be doing מלאכה. melacha. Okay, so it leaves open those two interpretations
of the משנה. Mishnah. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say, סברוה, savruha,
no, we actually started from the other end. סברוה, savruha, we assumed
מהלך לאו כעושה מעשה דמי mehalek lav ke'oseh ma'aseh dami
walking was not like you're currently working for the owner. והיינו טעמא
דמדאורייתא לא אכיל, v'hainu ta'ama d'mide'oraysa lo achil, and for that reason
you're not entitled to eat from the Torah when you're going from
one row to the next. משום דלאו כעושה מעשה דמי, mishum d'lav
ke'oseh ma'aseh dami, you're not currently doing any work for the owner.
הא עושה מעשה, ha oseh ma'aseh, were you doing work when you
were going from one row to the next, אכל מדאורייתא, achal mide'oraysa,
you would be entitled to eat. אלמא, alma, you see, עושה בגפן
זה אוכל בגפן אחר oseh begefen zeh ochel begefen acher that really
you would be allowed to eat grapes from one vine when you
were working on another. The only problem here is not that the
grapes were from a different vine, the only problem here is that
you're not currently doing any work, you're just walking. Gemara says, no,
no, that's not necessarily the problem. לעולם עושה בגפן זה אינו אוכל
בגפן אחר, le'olam oseh begefen zeh eino ochel begefen acher, that you
cannot eat from a different vine and that's why we needed the
תקנה. takana. We needed the תקנה takana because you were as you
were walking you were done with row A and you can't be
eating the grapes of row A if you're done with it. ומהלך
כעושה מעשה דמי, u'mehalek ke'oseh ma'aseh dami, the walking actually is doing
work, you are doing work for the owner and the problem was
not that you weren't doing work, the problem was that you were
eating the wrong grapes. Okay, so two interpretations of the משנה Mishnah
why we needed the special תקנה. takana. Did we need the special
תקנה takana because as you were going from row A to row
B you weren't doing work and therefore we needed the תקנה takana
to let you eat while you weren't doing work, or no, you
were doing work, but you were done with row A and we're
going to let you continue to eat the grapes of row A
even though you were done with it? So we don't have an
answer to our question that if you're eating working on one vine
can you eat from the other vine. Let's just finish to the
משנה. Mishnah. ובמחובר כשהיא פורקת ובחמור, u'v'mechubar keshi'hi porekes u'vachamor, you can
a donkey can eat when it is unloaded. So the גמרא Gemara
says כשהיא פורקת מהיכא אכלה? keshi'hi porekes meheicha achla? After it's unloaded
where's it eating from? Right? עבודה avodah is done, the work is
done. So why is it allowed to eat? אימא עד שתהא פורקת
eima ad shetehei porekes until it's unloaded, as the donkey is carrying
the stuff until you unload it it can eat. תנינא להא דתנו
רבנן tanina l'ha d'sanu rabbanan we taught what our rabbis taught, חמור
וגמל אוכלים ממשוי שעל גביהן, chamor v'gamal ochlim mimasoi she'al gabeihen, right
if you have these big bags, right, and a little hay is
sticking out, right, you know, they can stick turn their head around
and eat from the stuff that's being carried on their back. ובלבד
שלא יטול בידו ויאכילם. u'vilvad shelo yitol beyado v'yachilem.
You can't take the hay out of the bag and feed them,
right? The donkey eats naturally. You can't actually feed it. So what's
the חידוש chiddush here? So just one line in תוספות Tosafos what
the חידוש chiddush is, right? Is it just eating while it's working?
What's the חידוש? chiddush? So תוספות Tosafos says the חידוש chiddush is,
if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, דסלקא דעתך אמינא שאינה אוכלת אלא
כשהיא רואה הגפן לפניה d'salka daitach amina she'eina ocheles ela keshi'hi ro'ah
hagefen lefaneha
because what is the reason an animal's allowed to eat? We had
this discussion before. Is it the anguish of the fact that it's
not being allowed? So maybe there's no anguish here if the food
is on its back. Okay. או כשאינה רואה הגפן עליה או בעגלה
אינה אוכלת. o keshe'eina ro'ah hagefen aleha o ba'agala eina ocheles. Okay,
and then he asks this question which we asked before, ואף על
גב דטעמא דחסימה לאו משום דחזי מצטערת הוא. v'af al gav d'ta'ama
d'chasima lav mishum d'chazi mitzta'ares hu. And the גמרא Gemara said is
the problem that the animal is anguished or is the problem that
the animal isn't being fed? So because we raised that question before,
we might have thought that there might be a difference if the
food is on its back as opposed to if the food is
in front of it. Okay, and this teaches us otherwise. Okay, which
we...